[Music]
the high glycemic impact of potatoes may
increase the risk of type 2 diabetes
perhaps by chronically over stimulating
the insulin producing cells in the
pancreas
in my last two videos i explained that
you can decrease the glycemic impact of
white potatoes by eating them cold or
chilling than reheating them or adding
broccoli lemon juice or vinegar what
else can we do well if you remember i
had a video a few years back that showed
how the pigments in brightly colored
berries can act as starch blockers so if
you're going to eat a high glycemic food
you may be able to moderate its impact
by spreading raspberries on your toast
for example or adding strawberries to
your corn flakes or sprinkling
blueberries in your pancakes
no i'm not saying you have to put
blackberries in your baked potato but
given that the natural color compounds
in fruits can slow down starch digestion
what about
pigmented potatoes even just yellow
potatoes like yukon gold may be
preferable to white but the best
maybe purple potatoes not just purple
skinned potatoes but purple fleshed
potatoes
if you've never seen purple potatoes
they are remarkable they have almost a
neon blue glow and not only do they look
cool but purple potatoes cause less of
an insulin and blood sugar spike
compared to even the yellow flesh
potatoes suggesting that switching from
yellow or white to purple could have a
large potential public health benefit
how do we know it's the pigments
themselves that are responsible rather
than other differences between the
different potato varieties
researchers tried adding a control
comprised of berries and a potato starch
jelly but that would seem to add even
more variables
in a test tube extracts of purple and
red flesh potatoes connect to starch
blocker so hey if you can
extract and purify out the purple potato
pigments say that five times fast you
could remove any other effects of the
different potato varieties by adding the
purple pigments to yellow potatoes and
lo and behold compared to just plain
yellow potatoes you can get a
suppression of the blood sugar and
insulin spikes
this way you don't get that overshoot
reaction where your blood sugars can
actually drop below fasting like you
might get otherwise instead you get the
gentler up and down and blood sugars
you'd expect from a lower glycemic food
the authors suggest purple potato
extracts could be produced and made into
supplements or fancy
functional foods
but these health promoting compounds may
be more cost effectively received from
consuming purple potatoes themselves
if you were paying pretension you might
have caught in the title as it flashed
by that the pearl potato pigments may
also affect inflammation
the potato association of america likes
to paint potatoes as an
anti-inflammatory food but what they
don't tell you is that this benefit may
be limited to pigmented potatoes if you
randomize people eat a small white
potato every day for six weeks versus a
yellow or purple flesh potato the purple
potato group achieves significantly
lower levels of inflammation compared to
the white potato group measuring both
c-reactive protein and interleukin-6
pigmented potato consumption also alters
oxidative stress within hours of eating
a large purple potato you get a nice 60
bump in the antioxidant power of your
bloodstream and this translates into
less free radical dna damage
if you compare the antioxidant activity
of white potatoes yellow potatoes and
purple potatoes yukon gold has about
twice the antioxidant power of white but
purple has 20 times the antioxidants
which is comparable to what you might
see in berries
half a purple potato has about the same
polyphenol antioxidant complement as
half a cup of blueberries
purple potatoes can increase the
antioxidant capacity of our bloodstream
whereas straight white potato starch can
act as a pro-oxidant and decrease it
eat a purple potato and over the next
eight hours the antioxidant capacity of
your bloodstream goes up in contrast if
you eat white potato starch devoid of
any pigment
you can end up worse off than where you
started
okay but does this translate into
different physiological effects
yes indeed half people eat either purple
potatoes or white potatoes for two weeks
and the purple potatoes improved a
measure of arterial stiffness whereas
the white potato did not and this
translates into a drop in blood pressure
even in those already taking high blood
pressure drugs suggesting purple
potatoes are an effective blood pressure
lowering agent
but what about the toxic glycoalkaloid
compounds in potatoes
the toxic human dose starts around two
to five milligrams per kilogram of body
weight and the lethal dose is not too
far behind
the average amount of total
glycoalkaloids in most potatoes however
is less than 100 milligrams per kilogram
so at the average american weight of 180
pounds a toxic dose is like four to nine
pounds of potatoes
what happens when you approach that
possible
nausea vomiting diarrhea that could
easily be confused with something like
gastroenteritis or food poisoning
some people can start to get sick at
just 1.25 milligrams per kilogram of
body weight or even one milligram per
kilogram that would only be about two
pounds of potatoes at the average
american weight it's also possible they
could start accumulating if you ate them
day in and day out
what about those people who go on a fad
potato diet eat meals three or four
pounds a day
they can do that without risking getting
sick only if they peel their potatoes
which removes nearly all the
glycoalkaloids
[Music]
so
you